<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
	<title>Managing resources</title>
	<para>WASP is designed to be flexible in that data processing flows can incorporate steps from other flows,
	providing sequencing facilities to tune processing and analysis to their liking and actual environment.  The
	standard processing flows are distributed as a guideline; however they may be modified as necessary to meet
	individual needs.
	</para>
	<section>
		<title>Overview of the standard flows</title>
		<para>The basic design of a massively parallel sequencing flow is presented in 
		<xref linkend="sequencingFlow" xrefstyle="select: label" />.</para>
		<figure id="sequencingFlow">
			<title>Overview of hierarchy of flows to complete a MPS analysis</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="figures/SequencingFlow.png" width="5.5in" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>The diagram is intended to give an overview of the complexity of tracking all of the steps from
		submission of a job through to sequencing and analysis of the samples.  This complexity is lessened
		for the developer by maintaining a modular system of flows, where a master job processing flow can be 
		configured to run using flows specific for machines, assays, and user selected analysis requirements.  
		</para>
		<para>WASP flows are abstracted away from eachother where ever it is possible to increase modularity.  
		For example, sequencing flows are abstracted away from analysis flows, so that generic analysis steps
		can be created to work on a common file type (for example FASTQ sequencing output).  Since most reference
		based aligners deal with the FASTQ format, new aligner classes can easily be developed and added to 
		existing pipelines, but does not preclude a particular implementation from going back and getting 
		data at another level (e.g. colorspace) since files are tracked with appropriate metadata and 
		are associated at the sample level. 
		</para>
	</section>
</chapter>